Finding Aid for William B. Cudlip papers, 1922-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William B. Cudlip papers
1922-1985
Cudlip, William B., 1904-
851032 Aa 2
Detroit, Michigan, attorney, Republican regent of University of Michigan; regent’s files; political materials; and personal miscellanea.
8.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of William B. Cudlip (donor no. 5442 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William B. Cudlip was born in Iron Mountain, Michigan on March 4, 1904. He attended Swarthmore College (1921-1922), then graduated from the University of Michigan Law School in 1926. After being admitted to the bar of Michigan, he joined the firm of Campbell, Bulkley & Ledyard in Detroit. He became a partner in the firm in 1933 and in the firm's successor, Dickinson, Wright, McKean & Cudlip. In 1961-1962, Cudlip was a delegate to the Michigan Constitutional Convention. In 1963, he was elected a Regent of the University of Michigan. He served one term until 1972. He had previously run unsuccessfully in 1945 and 1955. As regent, Cudlip served on a major gifts committee of the $55 Million campaign. He also undertook a survey of the legal status of the University, the results of which were published in 1969 under the title The University of Michigan: Its Legal Profile.
The Cudlip collection contains files relating to his activities as regent of the University of Michigan, 1963-1972, to his work as delegate to Michigan's Constitutional Convention, 1961-1962, and as general counsel for the Michigan Bankers Association, 1932-1953. In addition, there is personal and political correspondence, 1922-1985, detailing in part with his involvement in Republican Party affairs, especially his friendship with Michigan Senator Arthur H. Vandenberg and his support of Vandenberg's candidacy for the Republican nomination for president in1940. Other files include speeches relating mainly to banking during the depression; an essay, entitled, "Pages from the diary of a lumberjack"; and notebooks from his University of Michigan Law School classes, 1923-1926.
Subjects:
Banks and banking--Michigan.; Depressions--1929--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.); Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-2010.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Lawyers--Michigan--Detroit.; Logging--Michigan.; Michigan Bankers Association.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Presidents--United States--Election--1940.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. Law School. Class of 1926.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.Student notebooks.; Cudlip, William B., 1904-1988; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Barristers Society (University of Michigan); Buildings--Michigan--Marquette.; Cudlip, William B., 1904-1988; Detroit Club.; Iron Mountain (Mich.); Lake Shore, inc.; Marquette (Mich.)--Buildings.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan. Law School. Class of 1926.
Contributors:
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Regental papers, 1963-1972
  - Yearly files
    - 1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965 (Box 1)
      (folder 1 of 2)
    - (folder 2 of 2), 1965 (Box 2)
    - 1966, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1969, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1971, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1972, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Topical files
    - University of Michigan $55 million program
      - 1967, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Special Assignments (Box 5)
      - 1968 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan-Hospital Study and Advisory Committee (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan By-laws (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan By-laws (Box 6)
      (folder 2 of 2)
    - Lawyers Club, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Regental Committee on Administrative Salaries (Box 6)
    - Regents Salary Committee, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Johnson v. The University of Michigan (Indian Treaty Case) (Box 6)
    - Flint College (Box 6)
    - Selection of president, 1967
      - General (Box 6)
      - Candidates file (Box 6)
    - BAM strike, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Regental campaigns
    - Candidacy (letters), 1944-1945 (Box 6)
    - Campaign flyers/mailings, 1955 (Box 6)
    - Candidacy for regent of The University of Michigan, 1963; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Congratulatory letters, 1963 (Box 6)
- Personal correspondence, 1922-1985
  - 1922-1985, 11 folders (Box 7)
- Michigan Constitutional Convention material, 1961-1962
  - Printed material and election data, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - February-September, 1961 (Box 7)
    - October-December, 1961 (Box 7)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 7)
  - Style and Drafting Committee, 1962 (Box 7)
  - Printed material
    - Anti-constitutional Convention (Box 7)
    - Republican Party delegates (Box 7)
    - General, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Paper, "The Function of the States" (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous speeches (include related correspondence), 3 folders (Box 7)
- Republican politics, 1931-1951
  - Political correspondence, 1936-1947; 4 folders (Box 8)
    (include correspondence with Arthur H. Vandenberg)
  - A.H. Vandenberg correspondence
    - 1932-1951, 4 folders (Box 8)
- Personal / Biographical
  - Biographical/personal (Box 8)
  - Clippings (Box 8)
  - Speeches, 1926-1960s (Box 8)
  - Speech: Iron Mountain Man of the Year award (and related papers), 1970 (Box 8)
  - Articles and statements (primarily concerning banking), 1930s (Box 8)
  - Article: "Some legal aspects of guaranteed war loans" (and related correspondence), 1942 (Box 8)
  - Essay: "Pages from the diary of a lumberjack" (Box 8)
  - Essays (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
  - Michigan Bankers Association (programs and miscellaneous) (Box 8)
  - Swarthmore College student papers (Box 8)
  - University of Michigan student paper (Box 8)
  - Photographs relating to Cudlip's activities as regent of the University of Michigan, 1963-1972, to his work as delegate to Michigan's Constitutional Convention, 1961-1962, and to other professional interests. (Box 8)
  - University of Michigan Law School notebooks, 2 folders (Box 9)